<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bios [
	<!ENTITY reg "&#174;">
	<!ENTITY mdash "#8212;">
]>

<bios>
	
<bio>
<uri_name>annette_seitz</uri_name>
<full_name>Annette Seitz</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Annette Seitz, an Institute for Learning (IFL) Fellow, currently leads the secondary English language arts curriculum expansion work with the Pittsburgh Public Schools. Seitz has fifteen years of experience working with large, urban school districts on improving their literacy curriculum and professional development systems and supporting instructional leadership for improved literacy achievement. Major projects include work in Austin, Bridgeport, Cleveland, Denver, Kansas City, Missouri, Los Angeles, New York, Philadelphia, Providence, and Springfield, MA. Most recently, Seitz worked with Los Angeles Unified School District to develop an integrated English language arts curricula and lead the district-wide coach training. Previously, Seitz worked with the Springfield Public School District, Massachusetts to create nested learning communities through leadership development with principals, school visits, and on-going collaboration with central office directors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Development work with the Institute includes working as a member of the Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt;/Elementary literacy team, where she focused primarily on K-12 writing instruction with a particular emphasis on studying student work to assess student progress, guide instruction, and develop a deeper understanding of standards. Seitz is currently a member of the Disciplinary Literacy ELA team and develops tools to support literacy instruction and to support coaches as they work with teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before joining the IFL, Seitz held a joint position as Research Associate at the Learning Research and Development Center and the National Center on Education and the Economy (NCEE) in Washington, DC. While in this position, she edited the &lt;em&gt;New Standards: Performance standards in English language arts, mathematics, science, and applied learning&lt;/em&gt;, published in 1996. Seitz also spent three years working with the Board of Education in New York City as they customized and implemented new performance standards. As part of the NCEE literacy team, Seitz co-authored a monograph to help teachers prepare students to meet high standards in writing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seitz earned her B.A. and Higher Diploma in Education from the University College Galway (Ireland) and a Professional Certification in Secondary Education and a M.S. in Child Development in Literature and Literacy from the University of Pittsburgh. As a teacher at both the elementary and the high school level, Seitz developed a particular focus on writing instruction and designed and worked with curricular materials to improve rigorous literacy/writing instruction to maximize student learning and achievement.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>annette_seitz.jpg</pic>
</bio>

<bio>
<uri_name>bertha_reynolds</uri_name>
<full_name>Bertha Reynolds</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Bertha Reynolds is a former Research and Development chemist who has worked in the coatings and resins industry for ten years. As a Fellow with the Institute for Learning at the Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC), University of Pittsburgh, Reynolds is a member of the Disciplinary Literacy science team. In addition to her role with the IFL, Reynolds, in collaboration with Dr. Christian Schunn, serves as the content lead writer on the design and development team for an engineering design-based chemistry curriculum. She works with teachers in many local districts on the dissemination and implementation of this curriculum and reform of teaching practices. Reynolds is the Director of Curriculum Development for the Research Experience for Teachers (RET) program, run jointly through the University of Pittsburgh's LRDC and the School of Engineering. In this capacity, she provides professional development for participating high school teachers, guiding them through the process of designing curriculum materials for use with their students that embodies their engineering research experience. In addition, Reynolds co-directs the RET culminating event, Innovative Design Competition for High School Students. Reynolds has strong local connections, with both the independent and public school districts—she has served two terms as a trustee at Shadyside Academy, an independent school in Western Pennsylvania, serving as Chair of the Academic Program and Student Life Committee, and is a member of the Diversity Committee. She also volunteered as the Chair of the Parent Advisory Committee for Fund for Advancement of Minorities through Education (FAME).
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>bertha_reynolds.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>colleen_briner</uri_name>
<full_name>Colleen Briner</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Colleen Briner is the Chief Financial Officer of the Institute for Learning (IFL) at the Learning Research and Development Center of the University of Pittsburgh. She began working with the IFL in 2000, working as the Contract and Budget Administrator and then as the Assistant Director before being named Chief Financial Officer in 2010. She works in conjunction with the Executive Director to continuously shape and design the organization through detailed and systematic attention to its individual structures. Briner oversees fiscal and operational management, marketing initiatives, staff management and development, and program and product development. In addition to her work with the IFL, Briner has independent business consulting experience specializing in business plan writing and strategic marketing for small businesses. She is active in the Pittsburgh non-profit community through board and committee service. Briner holds a Master's degree in Public and International Affairs and a Master's degree in Business Administration from the University of Pittsburgh.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>colleen_briner.jpg</pic>
</bio>

<bio>
<uri_name>chris_hausammann</uri_name>
<full_name>Chris Hausammann</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Chris Hausammann joined the Institute for Learning as a Fellow in 2010. He is a member of the Disciplinary Literacy in English language arts team. Prior to his work at the Institute, he served as a mentor of instructional coaches at the Allegheny Intermediate Unit (AIU) in Homestead, PA, through a partnership with the Pennsylvania Institute for Instructional Coaching.  There he implemented a system of supports that included regular on-site visits and professional learning opportunities for coaches focused on changing instructional practices to improve student outcomes in their schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Chris brings many years experience to the IFL as a grade 7-12 English language arts teacher and high school literacy coach in the Keystone Central School District in Lock Haven, PA. Additionally, he has taught a number of ELA- and linguistics-related courses at the University of Pittsburgh, the Pennsylvania State University in University Park, PA, and the Pennsylvania College of Technology in Williamsport, PA.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Chris has a Bachelor of Science degree in Secondary Education (English) and his Master’s degree in Applied Linguistics from the Pennsylvania State University. Currently he is engaged in doctoral studies in the Language, Literacy, and Culture Program at the University of Pittsburgh.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>unknown.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>deborah_jordan</uri_name>
<full_name>Deborah Jordan</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Deborah Jordan is a Fellow of the Institute for Learning and a member of the Disciplinary Literacy science team. Prior to joining the IFL, Deb was a Science Educator with the Biological Science Curriculum Study (BSCS) where she served as a curriculum writer and professional developer. While at BSCS she directed the revisions for their elementary science curriculum &mdash; &lt;em&gt;BSCS Science Tracks: Connecting Science &amp; Literacy&lt;/em&gt;, provided literacy strategies for essays in &lt;em&gt;BSCS Biology: A Human Approach&lt;/em&gt;, served as a contributing author to &lt;em&gt;The Biology Teacher's Handbook&lt;/em&gt;, and co-authored the science chapter of &lt;em&gt;Content Matters: A Disciplinary Literacy Approach to Improving Student Learning&lt;/em&gt;. Deb provided professional development for National Academy for Curriculum Leadership institutes, Promoting Rigorous Outcomes in Mathematics/Science Education institutes, the Ministry of Education in Singapore as well as many districts across the nation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Deb began her career in science education as a classroom teacher. She served as a district science coordinator for six years providing professional development and facilitating the alignment of curriculum to state standards. During her seven years as an educational consultant with Mid-continent Research for Education and Learning (McREL), she provided professional development and technical assistance to numerous states and districts as well as contributing to many publications including Teaching Reading in Science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Deb has a Bachelor of Arts degree in Elementary Education from the University of Northern Colorado. Her Master's degree is in Special Education: Moderate Needs from the University of Northern Colorado.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>deborah_jordan.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>donna_bickel</uri_name>
<full_name>Donna DiPrima Bickel</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Donna DiPrima Bickel has been a Fellow of the Institute for Learning (IFL) at the Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC), University of Pittsburgh since 1998. She is currently a member of the PreK-12 English language arts team and former chair of the elementary literacy team. Dr. Bickel co-developed and leads the Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; (CFC) work of the IFL in elementary literacy, a program for preparing elementary literacy coaches on the use of Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt;, a rigorous model of professional development based on the IFL's Principles of Learning. Dr. Bickel produced and directed the video artifacts that form the core of this practice-based program and she has assisted central office leaders in Providence, RI, Pittsburgh, PA, Los Angeles, CA, New York, NY, El Paso and Austin, TX to create the conditions needed to support coaching effectiveness and provided professional development to literacy coaches learning to function in this challenging role. From 2006- 2010, Dr. Bickel was co-principal investigator with Dr. Lindsay Clare Matsumura, on an Institute for Education Sciences (IES) experimental design grant to study the impact of the Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; model on teachers' practice and student achievement in elementary literacy, and co-authored several papers on this work. Most recently, Dr. Bickel has supported coaching work in Guilford, CN and provided professional development to elementary school teams in Dallas, TX on learning to teach genre-based writing based on rigorous units of study developed at the IFL.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Bickel earned a B.A. from Hunter College (NY) and a Ph.D. from the University of Pittsburgh. Bickel has thirty years of experience in Early Childhood and Elementary Education as both a researcher and practitioner and has worked in higher education and public schools. She was the director of the Pittsburgh Public School's Work Sampling Project, where she coordinated and conducted professional development for administrators and teachers and supervised the implementation and evaluation of this performance assessment system in five schools. As co-investigator with Dr. Samuel Meisels, Dr. Bickel worked on one of the Pittsburgh Public Schools' Restructuring Evaluations which examined the impact of the use of Work Sampling on teachers, students, and parents. As an adjunct assistant professor in education at the University of Pittsburgh, she designed and taught two core courses in the Early Childhood Teacher certification program and, as an instructor, co-designed and co-taught a course in Instructional Leadership in the School of Education to aspiring principals. She has conducted local program evaluations for several national preschool programs, including EVEN START and Families for Learning, and has consulted locally and nationally on a variety of early childhood issues regarding curriculum, instructional practice, and assessment. She has taught regular and special education classes at the elementary level and is certified as a curriculum and instruction specialist for grades K-12 in Pennsylvania.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Bickel has a special interest in the production and use of digital video examples of teaching practice as a tool for professional development. She played a key role in collecting and writing commentary for the video examples for the &lt;em&gt;New Standards Primary Literacy Standards and for Speaking and Listening Preschool Through Third Grade&lt;/em&gt;, produced by the National Center on Education and the Economy and LRDC.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>donna_bickel.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>fran_mossberg</uri_name>
<full_name>Fran Mossberg</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Fran Mossberg is a Fellow of the Institute for Learning at the University of Pittsburgh. She conducts leadership development seminars in Minneapolis, Grand Rapids, and Fort Worth. Dr. Mossberg was employed for 30 years in the Providence Public Schools in Rhode Island as a high school teacher, an ESL/bilingual specialist, the director of the Student Registration and Parent Information Center, and as the director of the Department of Language and Culture. As director, she co-authored the Language Instruction for Transition (LIFT) Framework for Teaching and Learning for Bilingual, ESL, and Dual Language Programs, from grades K-12. Mossberg also served as the project manager between the Providence Public Schools and the Office for Civil Rights.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mossberg also worked for Teachers21 serving the Malden School Department in Malden, Massachusetts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Among her activities, she serves as co-chair for the Rhode Island Department of Education English Language Learners Advisory Council, which advises the Commissioner of Education on matters relating to second language learners. As a member of the Greater Providence Chamber of Commerce Leadership Rhode Island, she participates in enhancing the leadership capacity in Rhode Island while fostering a higher level of civic and community concerns. She also serves as vice president of the board of directors for Mentor, Inc. an educational non-profit organization.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>fran_mossberg.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>idorenyin_jamar</uri_name>
<full_name>Idorenyin (Ido) Jamar</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Idorenyin (Ido) Jamar is a Fellow at the Institute for Learning, Learning Research and Development Center, University of Pittsburgh. As a member of the Disciplinary Literacy mathematics team she has designed and facilitated professional development for teachers, coaches and administrators in urban districts around the country. Prior to working for the Institute for Learning, Jamar was an Assistant Professor of Mathematics Education at the University of Pittsburgh and Bayero Unversity (Kano, Nigeria) and has taught secondary mathematics in urban schools for eight years. She served on the editorial panel of Mathematics Teaching in the Middle School and has served on Advisory Boards for WestEd and the Pittsburgh Council on Public Education. She received a Ph. D. and M.S. in Cognitive Psychology and a B.A. in Applied Mathematics, all from Brown University, and is certified to teach secondary mathematics in Rhode Island and Pennsylvania.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>idorenyin_jamar.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>lauren_resnick</uri_name>
<full_name>Lauren Resnick</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Lauren Resnick is an internationally known scholar in the cognitive science of learning and instruction and Director of the prestigious Learning Research and Development Center from 1977-2008. She has researched and written widely on the learning and teaching of literacy, mathematics, and science. Her recent work focuses on school reform, assessment, effort-based education, the nature and development of thinking abilities, and the role of talk and discourse in learning. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Resnick is founder and Director of the Institute for Learning, which bridges the domains of research and practice by conveying to educators the best of current knowledge about learning processes, principles of instruction, and the design of school systems.  Dr. Resnick also co-founded the New Standards Project (1990-1999), which developed performance-based standards and assessments that widely influenced state and school district practice. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Resnick is a prolific author, a respected editor, and a frequent consultant, with appointments to many national education boards, commissions, and associations. Most recently, she was selected as the Wallace Foundation&apos;s Distinguished Lecturer at the April 2009 American Educational Research Association (AERA) conference. In mid-November, 2008, she chaired a symposium on education policy recommendations for the new presidential administration, developed by members of the National Academy of Education.  Those recommendations are being compiled into a report for wide distribution among scholars, practitioners, and policymakers. She is the current and founding editor of Research Points, a publication of the AERA. Her National Academy of Sciences monograph, &lt;em&gt;Education and Learning to Think&lt;/em&gt;, has been influential in school reform efforts, and her widely circulated Presidential Address to the American Educational Research Association, &quot;Learning In School and Out,&quot; has shaped thinking about youth apprenticeship and school-to-work transition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recognized both nationally and internationally, Dr. Resnick has received multiple awards for her research, including the 2007 Award for Distinguished Contributions in Applications of Psychology to Education and Training, the 1998 E. L. Thorndike Award, both from the American Psychological Association, and the 1999 Oeuvre Award from the European Association on Research for Learning and Instruction (EARLI).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Educated at Radcliffe and Harvard, Dr. Resnick has been an Overseer of Harvard University and a member of the Smithsonian Council.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>lauren_resnick.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>lawrence_charap</uri_name>
<full_name>Lawrence Charap</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Lawrence Charap has been a fellow at the Institute for Learning since 2007. He serves as the Chair of the history/social studies Disciplinary Literacy team. Prior to joining the IFL, Charap worked for six years at the College Board as an associate director for content and curriculum development in the Advanced Placement (AP) program. At the College Board, Charap oversaw the creation of content for the AP teacher web site, AP Central, directed professional development and curriculum issues affecting AP history and social sciences courses, and managed ongoing efforts to revise the AP United States History course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charap has taught in a variety of venues, most recently in the history department of the University of Rhode Island&mdash;College of Continuing Education, where he teaches the thesis course for history majors as well as twentieth-century U.S. history courses. Charap has also taught at Loyola College of Maryland, Towson University, and the Bryn Mawr School for Girls in Baltimore.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charap has a B.A. in history from the University of Chicago and a Ph.D. in American history from Johns Hopkins University. His research as a historian focuses on Jewish-Christian relations in the United States at the turn of the twentieth century. Other research and teaching interests include American cultural, intellectual, and ethnic history and the history of the U.S. from 1880 to 1940.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>lawrence_charap.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>luann_malik</uri_name>
<full_name>LuAnn Malik</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
LuAnn Malik joined the Institute for Learning as a Fellow in 2009. She is a member of the mathematics Disciplinary Literacy team, designing and delivering professional development in various districts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to joining the Institute for Learning, Malik worked for six years as a mathematics coordinator for the Southwest Pennsylvania Math Science Partnership project. In this position, she worked with district leadership teams and secondary math teacher leaders from 50 school districts in southwest Pennsylvania to strengthen student achievement in math and science.  In addition, she has eighteen years of experience teaching mathematics at the community college level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Malik has a Bachelor of Science in Education from Duquesne University and is certified to teach secondary mathematics in Pennsylvania and Colorado.  She holds a Master of Arts degree in Mathematics from the University of Colorado at Boulder.  Currently, she is a doctoral student in mathematics education under Margaret Smith at the University of Pittsburgh.  Her research interests include secondary math teacher content knowledge and professional development experiences that support teaching and learning using connections across multiple representations.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>luann_malik.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>monica_swift</uri_name>
<full_name>Monica Swift</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Monica Swift currently serves as a Fellow for the Institute for Learning (IFL) at the Learning Research and Development Center, University of Pittsburgh.  As a fellow with the IFL, Swift has worked with several school districts, some of which include: Baltimore, Los Angeles, Wilson, Guilford, and Dallas.  As a member of the Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; team in elementary literacy, Swift is currently working in Pittsburgh (Early Childhood Program and New Coach Training K-8) and El Paso, Texas (Education Service Center Region 19 Head Start) to support their implementation of high-quality literacy instruction and practice-based professional development using the Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; model of professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Swift brings a wide variety of educational experiences to her position as an IFL Fellow. She has worked in both the private and public school systems as a classroom teacher. Her experience includes work as a consultant for a curriculum company designing curriculum materials for a K-3 reading series. She has also worked for a non-profit educational agency which included designing and implementing a literacy professional development program for principals and teachers. In addition, she worked both as a literacy coach and consultant with the Institute for Educational Renewal (IER) at John Carroll University. In this role, Swift served as IER/IFL Liaison to the Cleveland Municipal School District (CMSD) working with central office leadership, instructional leaders, and school-based personnel. Swift further supported professional development efforts in the Cleveland Municipal School District (CMSD) by co-designing and facilitating a credited literacy course for CMSD teachers. In addition, Swift developed and facilitated professional development sessions for CMSD Early Childhood educators and the Cleveland Initiative for Education Curriculum and Assessment team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Swift earned a B.A. degree in Elementary Education at Hiram College and a M.A. degree in Education with a Reading Endorsement at Baldwin Wallace College.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>monica_swift.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>nancy_israel</uri_name>
<full_name>Nancy Israel</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Nancy Israel is the Executive Director of the Institute for Learning (IFL). She was the manager for the NetLearn and the High Performance Learning Communities Projects at the Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC). She manages the programs, staff, and budgets of the IFL. Israel is also actively involved in community and parent organizations in the Pittsburgh Public Schools and has co-chaired District-wide committees on restructuring the Pittsburgh Public Schools, been a member of the charter school review committee for Pittsburgh, and a member of the district&apos;s committee on equity and parity. She also sits on a city-wide board that serves as an oversight committee for the local public schools, as well as serves as the chair of the scholarship committee for another local organization. Israel has a Ph.D. in Policy and Administration.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>nancy_israel.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>nancy_owen</uri_name>
<full_name>Nancy Owen</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Nancy Owen is a Fellow of the Institute for Learning at the University of Pittsburgh. Nancy is a member of the Disciplinary Literacy Team and works with the K-12 ELA strand.  In addition, she has most recently conducted leadership development seminars in Dallas, Ft. Worth, Grand Rapids and Wilson (PA) School Districts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Owen retired from the Providence School District where she worked for 31 years. She was the Principal of a redesigned High School in Providence, Rhode Island. Owen was Providence's first administrator to facilitate a Site-based Managed School on the elementary level and had successfully gained the designation for Providence's first Site-based Managed High School. Owen has written, received and coordinated multiple grants for her school including a Disney Learning Partnership Grant, Comprehensive School Reform Grant, Magnet Schools Grant, Virtual Professional Development Schools Grant and Children's Crusade Grant in her elementary school. Her high school was recipient of a Carnegie Foundation Grant, New England Small Schools Network Grant, a Perkins Grant, and a Rhode Island School to Careers Grant. Owen was a Mentor Principal and worked with aspiring principals within her district. She received the title of Master Principal and served as Leadership Advisor to the Superintendent.  As a Reading Specialist, she conducted city-wide professional development focused on literacy improvement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
She has participated in a think tank funded by the Wallace-Reader's Digest Foundation and the Institute for Learning.  Owen served as core group member of the MacArthur Research Network on Teaching and Learning for six years.  During that time the network focused on analyzing the reasons for the slow and uneven pace of education reform and examining improvements in teaching and learning.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>nancy_owen.jpg</pic>
</bio>

<bio>
<uri_name>pam_goldman</uri_name>
<full_name>Pam Goldman</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Pam Goldman is the Institute for Learning&apos;s Senior Product Developer. In this role, she designs, co-authors, produces, and edits a series of study tools for educators based on the Institute&apos;s theory of action and practice of district and school reform. Goldman earned a B.A. in English from S.U.N.Y. at Buffalo and a J.D. from Northeastern University School of Law. Before joining the Institute, Goldman was an attorney in private practice with an emphasis on civil rights, labor law, immigration, and criminal law. She taught at Cornell Law School and the University of Kentucky College of Law. She has published scholarly articles on Kentucky history and on the history of the women&apos;s movement.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>pam_goldman.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>patricia_magruder</uri_name>
<full_name>Patricia Magruder</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Patricia Magruder is a Research Associate at the Institute for  Learning (IFL), Learning Research and development Center, University of Pittsburgh, and works as co-developer and district liaison for the Process Engineering for Educational Results (PEER) project.  She has an extensive background in K -12 systems reform and school-level instructional improvement.  Before joining the PEER project, she served as a Fellow with the Institute for Learning and was the lead liaison to the Los Angeles Unified School District.  Magruder is also a Harvard Executive Education Leadership Coach, recently completing an assignment as the lead coach to the Kentucky State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to her work with the University of Pittsburgh, Magruder was a Distinguished Educator for the Kentucky Department of Education.  In this role she provided leadership for curriculum, instruction, and assessment initiatives for Kentucky schools as part of the Kentucky Instructional Results Improvement System (KIRIS). Assigned to schools &quot;in decline,&quot; Patricia facilitated school improvement initiatives that resulted in achievement of &quot;successful school&quot; status within a two-year assessment period. Prior to this she filled the deputy superintendent’s role as Director of Planning, Budget, Research, Program Development and Technology for the Fayette County Public Schools in Lexington, Kentucky.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beginning as a Special Education teacher, Magruder has gathered experience as a university instructor at the Ohio State University and the University of Kentucky, a guidance counselor and administrator with the Upper Arlington City Schools, and a consultant with both the Ohio and Kentucky State Departments of Education and with the Prichard Committee for Academic Excellence. While working as a consultant to the Kentucky Department of Education, she was Chair of the Assessment and Accountability Design Team and a co-developer of the Kentucky Leadership Academy, a training program for superintendents, instructional supervisors, and principals, to support school reform efforts in Kentucky.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>patricia_magruder.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>rosita_apodaca</uri_name>
<full_name>Rosa E. (Rosita) Apodaca</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Rosa E. (Rosita) Apodaca was appointed an Institute for Learning (IFL) Fellow at the University of Pittsburgh on September 2001. Born in Texas and raised in Mexico, Rosita received her B.A. from the College of Saint Joseph in Albuquerque, New Mexico, her M.A. from The University of Texas at El Paso, and holds masters and doctoral degrees in Educational Leadership from Teachers College, Columbia University.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As the IFL liaison to the Austin ISD, Apodaca supports the district's efforts to improve teaching and learning. She has been instrumental in assisting the district in its pursuit of the formation of professional learning communities district-wide. AISD believes teachers need to talk to teachers, thus the district is making a concerted effort to help them have time for quality interactions so they can learn together. Apodaca co-constructed The Learning Walk&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; protocol for AISD with teachers and principals. The intent was to place teachers in charge of their learning thus making The Learning Walk&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; offshoot more coherent with the AISD goal of improving instruction while building community. Supporting principals and other administrators in the development of their instructional leadership acumen is also a high priority of her work in Austin. Being a boundary broker for IFL services and projects in Austin is an important part of her work.
&lt;/p&gt;
	
&lt;p&gt;
Rosita has recently been named liaison to the Region XIX Educational Service Center Head Start Program in El Paso, Texas and is looking forward to building new relationships and finding ways to support the leadership with the lofty goals they have for students, teachers, and other members of their learning community. She is also working with Prince George's County Public School's high school teachers on strengthening the educational Program for ELLs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apodaca is also spearheading development work for the IFL by investigating and pursuing new business development opportunities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During her appointment at the IFL, Apodaca has served as liaison to the Los Angeles Unified School District, the Hartford Public Schools, and the El Paso Independent School District lead for the Superintendents and Intermediaries Conferences, the Nested Learning Communities Product Development Project, and serves on the IFL Leadership Team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to joining the IFL, Apodaca served as a senior cabinet level officer in various urban school districts after holding teaching and other intermediary line and staff posts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
She has been a consultant to international, national, and local education agencies, served on professional advisory boards, authored books for teachers on language arts in Spanish for Spanish speaking students, and has written a number of articles in journals and professional publications. Apodaca co-authored, "Embedding disciplinary literacy: Leadership and professional learning" in the recently published book, &lt;em&gt;Content matters: A Disciplinary Literacy Approach to Improving Student Learning&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apodaca has served as an expert witness in Federal Court on the teaching and learning of English language learners and she is frequently invited to speak at national and international conferences on a variety of educational issues.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apodaca is currently a member of the American Education Research Association, the Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development, and the International Society of the Learning Sciences.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>rosita_apodaca.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>sam_spiegel</uri_name>
<full_name>Sam Spiegel</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Sam Spiegel (Ph.D.) is an Institute for Learning Fellow and chair of the Disciplinary Literacy science team. Dr. Spiegel also worked as a Science Educator in the Professional Development Center at Biological Sciences Curriculum Study (BSCS). Prior to joining BSCS, he served as Director of Research &amp; Development for a multimedia development company and as Director of the Center for Integrating Research &amp; Learning (CIRL) at the National High Magnetic Field Laboratory, Florida State University. Under Dr. Spiegel's leadership, the CIRL matured into a thriving Center recognized as one of the leading National Science Foundation laboratories for activities to promote Science, Technology, Mathematics, Engineering, and Technology (STEM) education. While at Florida State University, Dr. Spiegel also directed an award winning teacher enhancement program for middle grades science teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
His extensive background in science education includes experiences as both a middle school and high school science teacher, teaching science at elementary through college level, developing formative assessment instruments, teaching undergraduate and graduate courses in science and science education, working with high-risk youth in alternative education centers, working in science museums, designing and facilitating cyber-based courses, multimedia curriculum development, and leading and researching professional learning for educators. He was honored for his efforts in teacher education by the Association for the Education of Teachers of Science (AETS) with the Innovation in Teaching Science Teachers award (1997).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dr. Spiegel has been the invited keynote speaker to notable science education events such as the American Physical Society's Centennial meeting and the Shell Seminar at the National Science Teachers Association (NSTA) national conference. His publications include books, curriculum resources (print, manipulatives, DVD, Web, and CD-ROM media), research and professional practice articles, and numerous professional presentations.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>sam_spiegel.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>sandra_campo</uri_name>
<full_name>Sandra Campo</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Sandra Campo is a Fellow at the Institute for Learning and a member of the Mathematics Disciplinary Literacy team at the Institute for Learning, designing and delivering professional development in various districts. She served as co-chair of the middle school writing team for the College Board&apos;s SpringBoard program and currently continues to work nationally with this program. Additionally, Campo worked with the Frameworks Development and Assessment Committees at the Rhode Island State Department of Education. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Campo served for thirty-one years in the Providence (RI) Public Schools, working in both teaching and leadership roles. After teaching mathematics at both the middle and high school levels, and acting as Mathematics Department Head at the middle school, she also worked as a District Mathematics Resource Specialist at the central office. In this role, she designed and delivered professional development for K-12 teachers of mathematics. She co-managed the district&apos;s Saturday Academy, a program to provide additional support and instruction for middle and high school students. Since her retirement from Providence, she continues to work as coach at the elementary, middle, and high school levels.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sandra holds a Bachelor of Arts in Mathematics Education from the University of Rhode Island and a Master of Education in Urban Education from Rhode Island College.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>sandra_campo.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>stephanie_mcconachie</uri_name>
<full_name>Stephanie M. McConachie</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Stephanie M. McConachie is a Fellow at the Institute for Learning (IFL), Learning Research and Development Center, University of Pittsburgh. She currently co-leads the English language arts Disciplinary Literacy (DL) work. As part of this project, she has designed and led professional learning and curriculum development in English studies for school and district educators in ten urban school districts and a state consortium. Earlier, she coordinated the IFL's development team for the four core academic areas of Disciplinary Literacy. She was instrumental in developing the DL framework, design principles, and collaborative protocols. As part of the IFL, she has also served as a site liaison and worked with district and school leaders to improve principal instructional leadership and to support the development of coherent district instructional systems and routines. She has presented professional learning sessions at the National Staff Development Council, National Association of Teachers of English, and the Association of Supervision and Curriculum Development. She recently co-taught the Instructional Leadership course at the University of Pittsburgh School of Education. Her most recent publications include co-editing &lt;em&gt;Content matters: A Disciplinary Approach to Improving Student Learning&lt;/em&gt; book and co-authoring several of its chapters, including one on professional learning and leadership.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before coming to the IFL, McConachie led a variety of educational initiatives. She taught English and English Education to students from middle school through graduate school. She has also been a middle school principal, high school assistant principal, and an English language arts coordinator. As part of her district leadership position, she led the development of a K-12 writing curriculum. She is a past president of the Virginia Association of Teachers of English and a former co-director of a National Writing Project site. While a principal, she coached new principals as part of a National Association of School Principals program. She holds a doctorate in educational administration and a masters of arts in English education from the College of William and Mary.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>stephanie_mcconachie.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>victoria_bill</uri_name>
<full_name>Victoria Bill</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Victoria Bill is a former elementary and middle school mathematics teacher. She is currently a Fellow with the Institute for Learning at the Learning Research and Development Center, University of Pittsburgh. She serves as the Chair of the mathematics Disciplinary Literacy team for the Institute for Learning, where she works closely with Margaret Schwan Smith on the design and coordination of the practice-based professional development model for mathematics. She also developed and implemented a research-based elementary mathematics professional development course of study, which has been used in several of the IFL partner school districts. Collaborations that have added to her knowledge core and awareness of school systems include work with the National Alliance for Restructuring Education, the New Standards partnership, and the North Central Regional Laboratory. Bill&apos;s completion of a principal internship has also contributed to her understanding of school systems. She has co-authored several articles on mathematics instruction. Her most recent publications include a chapter in the book, &lt;em&gt;Content Matters: A Disciplinary Literacy Approach to Improving Student Learning&lt;/em&gt;, and an article on a lesson planning protocol, Thinking Through a Lesson Plan.  She has presented at professional conferences such as the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, the National Supervisors of Mathematics, the Pennsylvania Council of Mathematics Teachers, and the American Education and Research Association. She also teaches a Methods of Mathematics Instruction course for pre-in-service teachers at the University of Pittsburgh and an Instructional Leadership course at the University of Pittsburgh School of Education for teachers who aspire to be elementary or secondary principals.  Bill completed her studies at Carlow University and the University of Pittsburgh.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>victoria_bill.jpg</pic>
</bio>


<bio>
<uri_name>vivian_mihalakis</uri_name>
<full_name>Vivian Mihalakis</full_name>
<detail>
&lt;p&gt;
Vivian Mihalakis has been a Fellow at the Institute for Learning working with the Disciplinary Literacy English language arts team since 2005. Since joining the Institute, she has worked with various school districts including Fort Worth Independent School District, Grand Rapids Public Schools, Los Angeles Unified School District, Minneapolis Public Schools, and Pittsburgh Public Schools to improve the teaching and learning of English language arts. This work has included developing and supporting teachers to develop English language arts units for secondary school classrooms, and designing and implementing professional development for English language arts coaches using the Institute for Learning&apos;s Content-Focused Coaching&lt;sup&gt;&reg;&lt;/sup&gt; program. Before coming to the Institute, Mihalakis worked in both public and private, and urban and rural schools as an English language arts teacher. She has taught English language arts to students in grades eight through college, and taught secondary English language arts methods courses to Masters of Arts in Teaching and Professional Year students at the University of Pittsburgh. Mihalakis earned her B.A. from Allegheny College (Meadville, PA), her M.A. in Education from Lehigh University (Bethlehem, PA), and her Ph.D. from University of Pittsburgh.
&lt;/p&gt;
</detail>
<pic>vivian_mihalakis.jpg</pic>
</bio>

</bios>


